<tool id="blastxml_to_gapped_gff3" name="BlastXML to gapped GFF3" version="19.1.0.0">
  <description>converts blast results to a JBrowse-compatible file</description>
  <macros>
	<import>macros.xml</import>
	<import>cpt-macros.xml</import>
  </macros>
  <expand macro="requirements"/>
  <command detect_errors="aggressive"><![CDATA[
$__tool_directory__/blastxml_to_gapped_gff3.py
@BLAST_XML@

--min_gap $min_gap
$trim
$include_seq
> $output]]></command>
  <inputs>
    <expand macro="blast_xml" />
    <param label="Gap Size" help="Maximum gap in blast alignment, before a new match_part is generated" name="min_gap" type="integer" value="10"/>

    <param type="select" label="Trim sides of blast hits" name="trim">
        <option value="">Neither</option>
        <option value="--trim">Trim start and end</option>
        <option value="--trim_end" selected="true">Trim only end</option>
    </param>

	<param name="include_seq" type="boolean" label="Include protein alignment in Blast view in Apollo/JBrowse" truevalue="--include_seq" falsevalue="" />
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data format="gff3" name="output"/>
  </outputs>
  <tests>
      <test>
          <param name="blastxml" value="T7_NR.blastxml"/>
          <param name="min_gap" value="10"/>
          <param name="trim" value="--trim"/>
          <param name="include_seq" value="--include_seq"/>
          <output name="output" file="T7_NR_TO_GFF3.gff3"/>
      </test>
      <test>
          <param name="blastxml" value="input.xml"/>
	  <param name="min_gap" value="10"/>
          <param name="trim" value=""/>
          <param name="include_seq" value=""/>
          <output name="output" file="blast.gff"/>
      </test>
  </tests>
  <help><![CDATA[
**What it does**

Convert BLAST XML results into gapped GFF3 format with flexible options 
for visualization within JBrowse. This is critical for displaying the 
position of high-scoring pairs of the Target aligned against the Query.


The trimming option represents a unique feature among BLAST XML visualization 
tools allowing the user to view the complete alignment location information 
captured in the analysis.

When common BLAST visualization tools produce output like this::

.. image:: $PATH_TO_IMAGES/blast2html.png

This tool produces output which showing the true Subject sequence boundaries 
(start and end position) relative to your Query sequence::

.. image:: $PATH_TO_IMAGES/blast-extended.png

This can be useful for evaluating alternate start locations for your Query by 
allowing comparison with the Subject sequences found in the BLAST query.

In this example, the green bars on the top row of the JBrowse image indicate 
start codons. The BLAST hits and gene in the genome share an upstream start site. 
Here, the option to retain (not trim) the Subject sequence ends from the BLAST XML 
data allows that conclusion to be easily made. 

**Options::**

- **Neither** will not perform any trimming, therefore showing the entire protein alignment
- **Trim start and end** where both ends are trimmed, as in the standard BLAST HTML reports
- **Trim only end** removes the right end overhanging sequence, under the assumption that 
upstream sequence is more interesting, and since long tails result in poor visualization

By selecting **Include protein alignment…**, the actual sequence alignment will be displayed 
in the pop-up BLAST view in Apollo/JBrowse.

]]></help>
	<expand macro="citations" />
</tool>

