<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tool id="edu.tamu.cpt.primers.weight" name="Sequence Molecular Weight (MW)" version="1.0.0">
  <description></description>
  <macros>
    <import>macros.xml</import>
  </macros>
  <expand macro="requirements"/>
  <version_command>python weight.py --version</version_command>
  <command interpreter="python" detect_errors="aggressive"><![CDATA[weight.py
$fasta
> $output]]></command>
  <inputs>
    <param label="DNA Fasta File" name="fasta" type="data" format="fasta"/>
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data format="tabular" name="output"/>
  </outputs>
  <tests>
      <test>
          <param name="fasta" value="tm.fa" />
          <output name="output" file="mass.tabular" />
      </test>
  </tests>
  <help><![CDATA[
**What it does**

Calculates molecular weight of an input DNA sequence.

**How it works**

This section is taken from `OligoCalc's Documentation <http://www.basic.northwestern.edu/biotools/oligocalc.html>`__.

    DNA Molecular Weight (typically for synthesized DNA oligonucleotides. The
    OligoCalc DNA MW calculations assume that there is not a 5' monophosphate)

    Anhydrous Molecular Weight = (An x 313.21) + (Tn x 304.2) + (Cn x 289.18) + (Gn x 329.21) - 61.96

    An, Tn, Cn, and Gn are the number of each respective nucleotide within the
    polynucleotide. The subtraction of 61.96 gm/mole from the oligonucleotide
    molecular weight takes into account the removal of HPO2 (63.98) and the
    addition of two hydrogens (2.02). Alternatively, you could think of this of
    the removal of a phosphate and the addition of a hydroxyl, since this formula
    calculates the molecular weight of 5' and 3' hydroxylated oligonucleotides.

    Please note: this calculation works well for synthesized oligonucleotides. If you would like an accurate MW for restriction enzyme cut DNA, please use:

    Molecular Weight = (An x 313.21) + (Tn x 304.2) + (Cn x 289.18) + (Gn x 329.21) - 61.96 + 79.0

    The addition of 79.0 gm/mole to the oligonucleotide molecular weight takes
    into account the 5' monophosphate left by most restriction enzymes. No
    phosphate is present at the 5' end of strands made by primer extension, so no
    adjustment to the OligoCalc DNA MW calculation is necessary for primer
    extensions. That means that for ssDNA, you need to add 79.0 to the value
    calculated by OligoCalc to get the weight with a 5' monophosphate. Finally, if
    you need to calculate the molecular weight of phosphorylated dsDNA, don't
    forget to adjust both strands. You can automatically perform either addition
    by selecting the Phosphorylated option from the 5' modification select list.
    Please note that the chemical modifications are only valid for DNA and may not
    be valid for RNA due to differences in the linkage chemistry, and also due to
    the lack of the 5' phosphates from synthetic RNA molecules.

]]></help>
    <expand macro="citations" />
</tool>
