<tool id="genemarks" name="GeneMarkS" version="1.0.0">
<description>GeneMarkS</description>
	<command>
gmsn.pl --output $outfile
--clean --format ${format_flag}
$options
$file
	</command>
	<inputs>
	<param value="" name="file" optional="False" type="data" format="fasta" label="Input FASTA sequence" />
	<param value="" name="format_flag" type="select" label="Output format">
		<option value="GFF">GFF2</option>
		<option value="LST">LST</option>
	</param>
	<param value="" name="options" type="select" label="Genome">
		<option value="--prok">Prokaryote</option>
		<option value="--euk">Eukaryote</option>
		<option value="--virus">Eukaryotic viral genome</option>
		<option value="--phage">Phage</option>
	</param>

	</inputs>
	<outputs>
<data name="outfile">
	<change_format>
		<when input="format_flag" value="GFF" format="gff"/>
		<when input="format_flag" value="LST" format="txt"/>
	</change_format>
</data>
	</outputs>
	<help>
**What it does**

Gene predictor. Use `the conversion tool <root?tool_id=edu.tamu.cpt.gff3.reformat>`__ to convert to gff3.

**Abstract**

Improving the accuracy of prediction of gene starts is one of a few remaining
open problems in computer prediction of prokaryotic genes. Its difficulty is
caused by the absence of relatively strong sequence patterns identifying true
translation initiation sites. In the current paper we show that the accuracy of
gene start prediction can be improved by combining models of protein-coding and
non-coding regions and models of regulatory sites near gene start within an
iterative Hidden Markov model based algorithm. The new gene prediction method,
called GeneMarkS, utilizes a non-supervised training procedure and can be used
for a newly sequenced prokaryotic genome with no prior knowledge of any protein
or rRNA genes. The GeneMarkS implementation uses an improved version of the
gene finding program GeneMark.hmm, heuristic Markov models of coding and
non-coding regions and the Gibbs sampling multiple alignment program. GeneMarkS
predicted precisely 83.2% of the translation starts of GenBank annotated
Bacillus subtilis genes and 94.4% of translation starts in an experimentally
validated set of Escherichia coli genes. We have also observed that GeneMarkS
detects prokaryotic genes, in terms of identifying open reading frames
containing real genes, with an accuracy matching the level of the best
currently used gene detection methods. Accurate translation start prediction,
in addition to the refinement of protein sequence N-terminal data, provides the
benefit of precise positioning of the sequence region situated upstream to a
gene start. Therefore, sequence motifs related to transcription and translation
regulatory sites can be revealed and analyzed with higher precision. These
motifs were shown to possess a significant variability, the functional and
evolutionary connections of which are discussed.
	</help>
	<citations>
		<citation type="doi">10.1093/nar/29.12.2607</citation>
	</citations>
</tool>
