<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tool id="edu.tamu.cpt2.phage.fsfinder" name="Phage Frame Shift Finder" version="19.1.0.0">
    <description>finds possible frame shifts</description>
    <macros>
      <import>macros.xml</import>
		<import>cpt-macros.xml</import>
    </macros>
    <expand macro="requirements"/>
    <command detect_errors="aggressive"><![CDATA[
@GENOME_SELECTOR_PRE@

python $__tool_directory__/frameshift.py
$gff3_data
@GENOME_SELECTOR@

> $output]]></command>
    <inputs>
        <expand macro="gff3_input" />
        <expand macro="genome_selector" />
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
      <data format="gff3" name="output" label="Possible frame shifts in ${on_string}"/>
    </outputs>
    <help><![CDATA[
**What it does**

For the CDS features from an input GFF3, this tool looks for the duplicate amino acid hallmarks 
of canonical frameshifting sites and returns the possible frameshifted products as new features. 

**How it works**

The tool iteratively checks within the last 20 amino acids of the CDS for possible ORF starts in 
the -2, -1, +1, and +2 reading frames. Each possible ORF must have::

- a continuous reading frame at least half as long as the parent sequence.
- at least one amino acid the same as the two amino acids surrounding it in the zero-reading frame.
- at least five identical nucleotides in both the zero- and frameshifted- reading frame.

Possible frameshift sites are scored by their similarity to the canonical slippery sequence (XXXYYYZ).

.. class:: warningmark
This tool is noisy. Filter the results with care.

        ]]></help>
        <citations>
            <citation type="bibtex">
                @article{Xu200411,
                    title = "Conserved Translational Frameshift in dsDNA Bacteriophage Tail Assembly Genes ",
                    journal = "Molecular Cell ",
                    volume = "16",
                    number = "1",
                    pages = "11 - 21",
                    year = "2004",
                    note = "",
                    issn = "1097-2765",
                    doi = "http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2004.09.006",
                    url = "http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1097276504005398",
                    author = "Jun Xu and Roger W. Hendrix and Robert L. Duda",
                    abstract = "A programmed translational frameshift similar to frameshifts in retroviral gag-pol genes and bacterial insertion elements was found to be strongly conserved in tail assembly genes of dsDNA phages and to be independent of sequence similarities. In bacteriophage λ, this frameshift controls production of two proteins with overlapping sequences, gpG and gpGT, that are required for tail assembly. We developed bioinformatic approaches to identify analogous −1 frameshifting sites and experimentally confirmed our predictions for five additional phages. Clear evidence was also found for an unusual but analogous −2 frameshift in phage Mu. Frameshifting sites could be identified for most phages with contractile or noncontractile tails whose length is controlled by a tape measure protein. Phages from a broad spectrum of hosts spanning Eubacteria and Archaea appear to conserve this frameshift as a fundamental component of their tail assembly mechanisms, supporting the idea that their tail genes share a common, distant ancestry. "
                }
            </citation>
		<expand macro="citation/mijalisrasche" />
        </citations>
</tool>
